[music]
>> Close to the city of Xi'an in
northwestern China lies a vast and
ancient mausoleum, the burial ground of
the mighty Tang Dynasty.
The Tang Dynasty must have been one of
the most powerful [music] empires in the
world.
The Tang Dynasty lasts for more than 300
years.
>> [music]
>> And when Chinese look back, they
consider this period is one of the most
powerful dynasty in their history.
It was here in 1960 that a team of
Chinese archaeologists made an
extraordinary discovery.
As soon as you discover a tomb or some
other remains that are able to
corroborate texts, that makes [music]
archaeologists, epigraphers, and
researchers in China incredibly excited.
They opened one of the smaller tombs. It
belonged to a young princess who had
lived more than 1,200 years before.
What they found inside astonished them.
It's one of the largest Tang Dynasty
tomb discovered so far. They're very
important archaeological discoveries
vital [music] to our understanding of
both life and afterlife in Tang Dynasty.
It was a treasure trove, but not one of
silver or gold. The treasure was on the
walls.
The first session of the mural painting
depicts the official guardian guarding
the tomb. And the second part of the
tomb is about her personal life. And the
last session of the mural painting, that
is where the coffin was found.
It has a creation of an afterlife by
giving her the spaces that would be
appropriate for her. An amazing find.
In those chambers of death, they found
life.
The Terracotta Army,
one of the wonders of ancient China.
Thousands of warriors, forces, acrobats,
and musicians all buried in the earth to
accompany the first emperor of China
into the afterlife.
It was discovered by accident in 1974.
The Terracotta Army has since become a
UNESCO World Heritage Site and one of
the most popular tourist destinations
[music]
in modern China.
But just 60 miles away lies another
burial ground of China's imperial past
and another wonder.
The murals discovered in the tombs of
Chen Ling Mausoleum offer an
unprecedented glimpse into the life
during the Tang Dynasty,
a golden age in Chinese history when
they ruled an empire larger than that of
The great dynasty began in the year 618.
The last emperor had been assassinated.
China was engulfed in civil war, but
from the chaos a new ruling family
arose.
It's really started with the Lee family
seizing power from the declining Sui
Dynasty. [music] China has been suffered
from a
almost 500 years uh
civil war. So, soon after the Tang
Dynasty unified China again, it
developed uh fast uh
in economic and then
culturally. The ruling family of the
Tang Dynasty, the Lee family, they were
uh Turkic-speaking
aristocratic [music] family from the
northwestern regions of China.
>> [music]
>> The new dynasty would rule China for
almost three centuries. [music]
It was an era of progress and stability.
Art and literature blossomed, [music]
as did science and technology. And the
Tang capital, Xi'an, became [music] the
greatest city on the planet.
>> [music]
>> Today, the modern metropolis of Xi'an is
built on the site.
Few remnants of the Tang capital remain.
But the Great [music] Wild Goose Pagoda
in the south of the city is one.
Dating to the mid-7th [music]
century, it offers a hint of Xi'an's
lost grandeur.
>> [music]
>> The original Tang capital would have
been completely flattened at the end of
the dynasty. You wander around the city
walls today, you can still get a feel,
get a sense of [music] this amazing
city. The Tang capital had
uh dozens of huge and [music]
well-sponsored temples. Some of the
towers and pagodas being constructed
would have been up to 60 or 70 m high.
Uh you know, that's an amazing landmark
on a skyline. Xi'an being the capital of
the whole planet, it gathered a lot
merchant and religious people [music]
and even visitors from all over the
world.
Its name meant "perpetual peace",
but Xi'an was the center of a vast
empire. The Tang's influence stretched
into [music] modern Vietnam and Korea in
the east and into Afghanistan in the
west. At the empire's zenith, more than
50 [music] million people lived under
Tang rule.
The emperors commanded armies of 500,000
professional [music] troops, but Tang
dominance in Central Asia was not
unchallenged. Rebellions and incursions
were a constant threat.
And to the west [music] lay an even
greater enemy, the mighty Tibetan
Empire. For centuries, the [music] two
powers jostled for dominance. At times,
they would settle their differences
through diplomacy and intermarriage,
but at other times, only a military
solution would do.
There would be cycles of invasion and
occupation, counterattack and rebellion.
Control of trade routes was fiercely
contested as well. For mighty though the
Tang armies were, the triumph of the
dynasty was built on the flow of goods,
on the movement of people,
>> [music]
>> and the exchange of ideas.
Don't forget that the ruling family of
the Tang dynasty, [music] even within
their DNA and their cultural history had
these strong ties to nomadic people and
that carried on in the way that the Tang
Dynasty itself was structured. These
connections and the signs of these
connections became part of Tang Dynasty
[music] kingship. So for example,
receiving ambassadors, receiving traders
from foreign countries became
one way for the Tang Dynasty to
as it were reflect on itself. Culture,
commerce, ideas, [music] technology,
almost every aspect of life in Tang
Dynasty China was connected with a
broader regional [music] cultural
economy. Well, the Tang Dynasty acquired
all this new material forms and crafts.
For example, glass, gold and silver.
And also new religions like Buddhism,
Zoroastrianism and [music] Manichaeism.
People,
luxuries, goods, all kinds of things
were coming in and out constantly.
The Tang established sea routes to
Persia, to Egypt, to Mesopotamia and
beyond.
But it was by land the greatest
treasures flowed along a legendary trade
route to the west, the Silk Road.
The Qianling Mausoleum in northwestern
China is a window into another time. Of
the 19 tombs in the complex, only those
of Princess Yongtai and four others have
been opened.
But in the murals found within, the 7th
century heyday of the Tang Dynasty
[music]
is brought to life in stunning detail
and color.
Their scenes show a wealthy, diverse
society where customs, goods, and
fashions of foreign lands were welcomed,
integrated, reinterpreted, [music]
and made together into something unique.
It was a melting pot, impossible [music]
to imagine without the network of trade
routes which linked Tang China and the
world.
The Silk Road stretched from the west of
the Tang capital of Xi'an. Its merchant
[music] caravans skirted the mountain
ranges of Central Asia. They threaded
the valleys of Afghanistan [music]
and crossed the Karakum Desert. And on
and on they went towards the Caspian
Sea, the Black Sea, and Europe beyond.
The Silk Roads is a term
>> [music]
>> coined by a German geographer von
Richthofen in the late [music] 19th
century to refer to an extensive network
or of nodes
used for trade in essentially the
medieval period, sometime [music]
between 3rd and 4th century and right up
to around period of the Mongol conquest,
13th-14th [music] century. So, about
1,000 years of medieval history.
The Silk [music] Road is the mainstream
to make prosperity
of the Tang Dynasty financially and
culturally.
Silk Road is actually passed for
communication, migration, and trade that
used to be used [music] back in the
history.
It's a complex network of oasis towns
which essentially join China with the
central and western parts of Asia.
The people who dominated the Silk Road
[music] of the Sogdians.
The Tang Chinese, the Tang state was
invested hugely in the infrastructure of
the Silk Road [music]
because
they wanted, they valued the imports and
they valued the import-export business.
[music]
But the actual
trading was dominated by Central Asians
rather than by
Tang Chinese themselves along the route
itself.
The Silk Road which connected [music]
Tang China to the West had its origins
centuries earlier.
The Greeks under Alexander the Great had
pushed east as far as India.
Two centuries later, their [music]
descendants in Central Asia were met by
Chinese embassies of the Great Han
Dynasty.
A Chinese military presence [music] in
the region followed, securing the first
open trade route across the continent.
The Han coveted the horses bred further
west which were stronger and faster than
their native breeds.
Chinese luxury such as silk went the
other way passing from merchant to
merchant across thousands of miles
making many rich along the way.
But such a [music] lucrative trade route
was jealously contested. Every power in
the region wanted its peace and
opportunistic bandits were always ready
to swoop on the unguarded [music] and
unprepared.
The Han Dynasty fell in the 3rd century.
The Roman Empire too would soon
fracture. The Silk Road closed.
It was not until the Tang unified China
and expanded into Central Asia again in
the 7th [music] century that the direct
link to Europe was reopened and it would
carry far more than just silk.
>> [music]
>> There are more than silk which were
traded along the Silk Road. There are
also glass, gold and silver. It's also
very important to develop of Chinese
cuisine including all sorts of spice and
new fruits like melons and grapes and
walnuts. For the first time Chinese
started enjoy
>> [music]
>> uh
wine made of grape
because before that the Chinese wine is
usually made of rice or sorghum.
Many other things other than [music]
silk were moving across the Silk Road
including uh things to do with medicine,
>> [music]
>> ideas, people, warfare, luxuries, all
kinds of things.
It's very interesting from the mural
painting we [music] discover a lot
evidence about during this time China
has adopt a lot culture activity from
the Central Asia. For example, the first
time we see the Chinese start [music] to
play the polo. This all never happen in
China before.
Probably the most important set of ideas
[music] that traveled along the Silk
Road into China would have been
Buddhism. There's all kinds of sutras
[music] were coming from India and
triggering and stimulating uh new
interest in [music] this particular
religion and faith. It was a huge
stimulus to the history of ideas in
medieval [music] China.
Along with religious ideas, there also
came [music] new architectural plans
like Buddhist pagoda into China. There
were also new decorative elements like
the very popular pearl borders which
were
extensively used in Tang Dynasty
textiles.
The Silk Road enriched the Tang Dynasty
in more ways than one, [music]
and it made control of the empire all
the more tempting a prize for the
ruthless and ambitious. There was none
[music] more ruthless and ambitious than
the woman who rose from courtesan to the
highest throne in the land,
>> [music]
>> one of the most extraordinary figures in
Chinese history, Wu Zetian.
She was born in 624. [music]
Her family was wealthy and an early
backer of the new Tang regime.
That saw her [music] place in the
imperial court as a lesser concubine to
the emperor. She was 14 years old. She
watched, she learned, and she waited for
her moment.
Wu Zetian started as a concubine of the
second emperor of the Tang Dynasty,
[music] Emperor Tai, but she must be a
very charming woman.
Um that's why after Tai Emperor Taizong
died, she was actually taken again into
court by Taizong's son, Emperor Gaozong,
[music]
as his concubine at that time.
And then later she became the empress.
Unfortunately, 5 years later Emperor
Gaozong got a stroke. So, after that Wu
Zetian took over the power
and become the empress dowager, and
eventually she [music]
claimed herself emperor of China. She
would have retained a lot of power from
behind the curtain, as it's called, but
uh clearly didn't wish to relinquish it.
Her husband, Emperor Gaozong, faded away
and died in 683.
Their son [music] inherited the throne,
but he proved too independent-minded for
his mother,
>> [music]
>> and she deposed him after just 2 months.
She sent the young man into exile and
installed his younger brother as her
puppet. In 690, [music]
she then removed him, too, and seized
ultimate power herself.
She was the only female in the history
of China who actually became a emperor.
She ran [music] the state for more than
40 years.
Firstly, unofficially [music] as an
empress, then afterwards she claimed
herself an emperor. It's important to
say also this is one of the great
moments of flowering of Chinese [music]
culture. She was a great sponsor of arts
and religion. And so many of the
religious organizations
and artists would have thrived and
flourish under her patronage.
But she [snorts] was ruthless and
[music] she was clearly very power
hungry and also quite insecure and
didn't hesitate to execute or demote or
banish anyone who came up against her.
>> [music]
>> Wu Zetian's secret police stamped out
any dissent. Old and powerful families
who might threaten her were repressed.
In their place, she promoted those whose
loyalty would be to her alone.
But the imperial court soon became
[music] a nest of factions vying for
favor.
The wrong word in the wrong ear could
mean death and even her closest family
were not safe. In her rise to power, it
is said Wu Zetian killed her infant
daughter to frame and discredit a rival.
By the time she was emperor, she had
lost none of that calculating brutality
as her granddaughter Princess Yongtai
was soon to discover.
At the beginning of the 8th century,
[music] China was ruled by an aging
despot.
Wu Zetian had begun life at court as a
lowly concubine, [music]
but through her cunning and her
brutality, she had seized power, deposed
her own children, and declared a new
dynasty of her own.
>> [music]
>> The Empress was growing old, however.
She relied more and more on her two
lovers,
the Zhang brothers, Yi Qi and Zhang
Zhong.
The Zhangs grew powerful and made
enemies.
Among those whispering against the
brothers were two of Wu Zetian's
grandchildren, the teenagers Prince Li
Xian and Princess Yongtai. [music]
Princess Yongtai was obviously said to
be a great beauty who
if she stood next to plum blossoms, the
plum blossoms would look drab. Prince Li
Xian's name is Li Chongrun.
He is a grandson of Emperor Gaozong and
Empress Wu Zetian, but when Empress Wu
Zetian was in power, he got himself into
trouble by criticizing his grandmas.
Um unusually intimate relationship with
two male officers and her trust towards
them.
>> She
displayed what would have been regarded
as very corrupt behavior by favoring her
favorites with business deals and
status, titles, elevating them
essentially far beyond, as it [music]
were, their worth.
Wu Zetian discover a Princess Yongtai
and her brother and her husband talk
about her private life behind her back.
She got very annoying.
Their youth and family connections were
no defense. Wu Zetian's vengeance was
swift. Li Xian, Yong Tai and her husband
were all sentenced to death.
There are different records about their
death. So, Prince Li Xian supposedly was
killed to death.
But there are different stories about
the death of Princess Yong Tai. It's not
entirely clear. Her epitaph says she
died in childbirth, but it's more likely
that she was poisoned
and by the Empress Wu. Archaeologists
and also scholars have discovered
her brother and also her husband
were died just one day before her. So,
this coincidence seems unlikely to
happen. She died in a childbirth.
So, now most of the scholars has have
agreed that she was killed by her own
grandmother, Wu Zetian.
But Wu Zetian's grip on power was
fading.
Despite the risks, a plot was hatched to
remove her favorites, the hated Zhang
brothers. [music]
When she fell ill early in 705,
the conspirators made their move. The
brothers were killed and the ailing
empress forced to abdicate. The son she
had deposed 20 years earlier reclaimed
the throne. Wu Zetian's dynasty was
over.
Old crimes were [music] wiped away with
it.
Princess Yong Tai and her brother were
reburied. Magnificent new tombs were
built for them.
A ringing statement of the break [music]
with the old regime.
>> The tombs, for a start, [music] are
exceptionally large, sometimes several
hundred meters by several hundred
meters.
Both tombs share the same structure with
two large tomb chambers underneath
[music]
a truncated mound above ground. And
these two chambers were linked with a
short corridor, [music]
and they were approached by a sloping
tomb passage with a ground-level [music]
opening.
Remember we're in a world of sumptuary
laws here, where according to your
status on the social hierarchy, that
determines what
>> [music]
>> kind of luxury you can be and must be
afforded for everything in life and in
death.
>> [music]
>> And Princess Yongtai was treated with
great honors similar to that of an
empress.
The grand tombs of Princess Yongtai and
her brother were sealed up in the year
705,
but as the decades and centuries passed,
the ways in were forgotten.
All of these tombs are basically all
marked by a very grand spirit way
[music] flanked by large stone statues
which lead to a massive tomb mound
[music] or a actual mountain.
There would originally have been guards
and guardians and keepers living on
site, but once a dynasty has fallen,
there's no reason for that, and they
gradually, you know, [music] would have
melded into the into the landscape.
It's can be very difficult to actually
locate where [music] exactly the tomb
chambers are. Are they underground
underneath a big grave mound or within
the big mountain. So, if you see the big
mound there, but you still don't know
from where you dig into and to locate
the tomb chambers where everything is
buried.
The majority of the Tang tomb was
rediscovered soon after the Cultural
Revolution. China started to open to the
outside world. So, they need more
accommodation hotel [music]
to accommodate the visitors. So, they
have a huge construction work [music]
everywhere in China.
And this is the main period
a lot
Tang tomb has been discovered.
Archaeologists began the first
scientific excavations [music]
of the Qianling Mausoleum in the 1960s.
The teenage prince and princess would
have been buried with a treasury of
gold, silver, and jade.
But that was nowhere to be found in
their tombs. It's been looted and lost
in the many [music] centuries since.
The tombs of the Qianling area were
probably looted by the end of the Tang
Dynasty or if not shortly afterwards. I
think most of the stories are that it
was probably soldiery or bandits who
would have done the looting. [music]
Looters will only be able to take what
is portable. They probably couldn't have
taken very heavy objects like heavy
sarcophaguses or very heavy bells. So,
they would have gone for objects of
value, things made [music] for example
of silver.
All objects made of precious materials
like gold and silver or jade were taken.
So, for example, in the tomb of Prince
Zhanghuai, there was a jade book with
gilded inscription which indicate his
identity. [music]
So, that jade book was
broken down into pieces and took it away
and took it away. And only fragments
remained in the tomb.
But the thieves were less interested in
pottery.
Hundreds of ceramic figures were left in
Princess Yongtai's tomb alone.
And there was another thing the raiders
did not steal.
The stunning frescoes which lined the
tomb walls.
You have recreations of court scenery,
of the capital scenery, and of massive
processions and events.
The first section of the mural painting
depicts the official guardian guarding
the tomb. And the second part of the
tomb is about her personal life. And the
last section of the mural painting, that
is where the coffin was found.
What gets painted in the tombs are all
the things that the occupant is going to
need in the afterlife.
So, if that means for example that they
must be accompanied by a dozen beautiful
ladies-in-waiting, then they must be
painted there.
If it also means that they must have
musicians [music] and dancers,
bodyguards, if they must be able to
witness great military parades and
pageants, if they must live in fantastic
buildings and be fed marvelous food, the
wherewithal must all be there.
We don't know any names of those
craftsmen who created the mural
paintings within the tombs and also the
the ceramic figures, despite that their
works are very fine, high quality.
As they say, a picture is worth a
thousand words. The content [music]
of the images gives us a way to imagine
all kinds of everyday scenes that we
would never have otherwise been able to
conceive of. Only few of the Tang
Dynasty painting have survived. They
were originally painted in silk. So,
this discovery of the mural painting
help us to understand [music] their
daily life.
What's interesting about the Tang period
and these murals is that we're not just
looking at them introspective [music]
China. We're looking at China that is
fully integrated into a massive regional
economy across Eurasia, which means that
there would have been
ambassadors and traders and merchants
[music] and emissaries and all sorts of
other people
in the capital at the time. And of
course, they find their way into these
murals as well.
On the walls of the Qianling tombs, we
see Persian wine glasses and foreign
[music] dignitaries. We see musicians
and instruments from far-off lands. We
see cheetahs and camels and other exotic
beasts.
We see all the world coming to Tang
China [music] to trade, to pay tribute,
to serve, and to make a new life.
And we see the change in women's status,
[music] too.
The society definitely became more
tolerant and vibrant with all the
nomadic fashions coming in.
And there was definitely much less
social um segregation
of women. The women in the Tang Dynasty,
they enjoy much higher social status
>> [music]
>> in the society than any period
uh in Chinese history. They start to
dress up and imitate the European style
or even the fashion from the Central
Asia in many ways in their makeup, in
their dress, and [music] even their
social life.
We're still in the medieval period. It
is still a patriarchal [music] system.
The place of women is to correspond to
men, to be demure, and not to come out
from behind the curtain.
But that said,
women could ride horses.
Women might even have played polo. They
could certainly get out and about,
aristocratic women, that is. I imagine
that in a broader historical scheme,
[music]
their status was considerably higher and
they had more freedom, especially than
they did in the latter half of the of
the dynastic [music] period.
But this [music] outward-looking society
would not last forever.
>> [music]
>> Even as Tang China reached its zenith,
there were forces at [music] large in
the empire which would tear the dynasty
apart.
>> [music]
[music]
>> By the middle of the 8th century, Tang
China was at the peak of the golden age.
Wu Zetian's divisive [music] reign was
over.
Under the rule of her grandson, Emperor
Xuanzong, China enjoyed decades of
political stability, peace, and
prosperity.
>> [music]
>> The Tang dynasty must have been one of
the most powerful empires in the world,
if not the most powerful, in the
medieval period. It had much larger
population, and it had [music] a far
greater trading status that compared to
any other state of the time.
This very open hour in the China from
all the cultural and population exchange
>> [music]
>> came into a full bloom in the Tang
Dynasty.
The tombs themselves are a great mark
of, you know, the scale of the tombs,
you know, several hundred meters by
several hundred meters. It's an
indication of the wealth, the luxury,
the power, and what the status of China
was among the regional powers that
traded with it, that that recognized it.
In December 755,
however, disaster struck. An Lushan was
a powerful general in the Tang army and
a favorite of the emperor,
but he had a bitter rivalry with the
emperor's chief minister. After one
provocation too many, An Lushan
rebelled.
Civil war beckoned in China. With the
mighty northern garrisons under his
[music] command, An Lushan swept
southwards. Within months, his armies
had captured the great city of Puyang.
There, he declared himself the first
emperor of a new dynasty, the Yan.
He marched onwards to Chang'an. The
emperor fled. The city fell. An Lushan
was unable to secure the whole country.
Indeed, he could not even rule his own
family. Early in 757,
he was murdered by his son.
He, in turn, was killed by a loyalist to
the dead general.
The new Yan dynasty was imploding.
The rebellion failed,
but for the Tang, victory came at a
cost.
The economy was in tatters.
Thousands upon thousands had died, and
more had been forced to flee their
[music] homes.
The capital, Chang'an, had been looted.
The central bureaucracy there was
decimated.
The glue, as it were, that was holding
the state together started to come
apart, and you start to get the
you start to get rebellions, you start
to get independent governors, and that's
a recipe for [music] a disaster for a
for a unified centralized state.
>> A further series of um agrarian
rebellions [music] finally torn down the
dynasty
uh in the beginning of 10th century. The
Tang dynasty never recovered from the
756 An Lushan [music] Rebellion, even
though in name it carried on right up
until 907.
>> [music]
>> As the power and authority of the Tang
withered, so did their control over the
western regions.
Their old rivals, the Tibetan Empire,
swooped in. The Silk Road, which had
brought the Tang such prosperity, was
closed.
The 9th century then saw a series of
natural disasters and another
devastating uprising [music] against
imperial authority. This time, there
would be no recovery.
In 907,
the last Tang emperor was forced from
the throne. After ruling China for
almost 300 years, the great dynasty was
over.
China entered a new age of political
upheaval as the once unified [music]
state collapsed into rival kingdoms. But
the triumphs of the Tang dynasty were
not [music] forgotten. And though their
reign ended more than 1,100 years ago,
the legacy of Tang China can still be
felt today.
The impact on Chinese history has been
immense.
They defined many of the institutions
and institutional practices that come to
help us identify what their culture is.
>> [music]
>> I I the Tang Dynasty really has left a
lasting legacies in Chinese culture.
It's renowned for its literature
and it's ceramics. Also, it is the
woodblock printing started in China. So,
these are all the lasting legacies in
Chinese material culture which still
were important in our daily life.
If you take for example something like
the civil service examination system for
recruitment of officials to government,
you know, that was founded in the Han
Dynasty, but it really only became a
meritocracy in the Tang Dynasty. And
towards the middle towards the end of
the Tang Dynasty, you start to get men
coming into government [music] who are
often from obscure families, but are
brilliant. And a mechanism was found
within the system
to enable them to rise to the top and to
become advisers to government. So, these
kinds of institutional frameworks are
hugely important. Not to mention things
also like calligraphy in the history of
calligraphy,
essentially by the early Tang Dynasty,
the modern script which everyone writes
today was formed.
They still talk about the Silk Road.
They still want to revise the Silk Road.
So, you can see the new president Xi
Jinping, he emphasized so-called one
belt one road. This is one to echo their
golden period of Silk Road.
And when Chinese [music] look back, they
consider this period is one of the most
powerful dynasty in their history.
>> Stunning murals discovered in the tombs
of Princess Yongtai and Prince Yide have
opened our eyes to the wonders of the
golden age, but the earth may [music]
harbor more secrets still. Many of the
tombs of the Qianling Mausoleum have not
been excavated. [music]
Even greater treasures may yet come to
light.
It's a large tomb [music] complex with
the larger tombs for emperors and
empresses and [music] smaller what are
called satellite tombs for their
siblings, offspring, or for meritorious
officials or generals or people of that
kind. We know the imperial line. We know
the names of a lot of the the royals.
There will certainly be tombs [music]
that have not been discovered.
The main tomb in the Qianling Mausoleum,
the tomb of [music] the empress
Wu Zetian and emperor Gaozong are still
unexcavated. This is also probably the
only intact royal tomb that remain in
the mausoleum. I'm sure there are still
plenty of Tang arts waiting to be
discovered [music]
because during that time apart from the
royal tombs has been found in the
capital Xi'an, there are still some
high-ranking individual
>> [music]
>> that have been been buried in different
part of China and these tombs are still
waiting [music] to be discovered.
We will probably expect [music] to see a
lot more fascinating mural paintings, a
lot more valuable items, for example,
gold and silver in these tombs [music]
and also maybe very prominent artistic
work like calligraphy work.
There is still the legend that a divine
piece of calligraphic work by [music] a
Eastern Jin calligrapher Wang Xizhi was
in one of these imperial tombs of the
Tang Dynasties. I think Chinese
government sensibly has a policy of not
biting off more than it can chew and of
just dealing one by one with the major
tombs which require a huge amount of
archaeological resource and effort
[music] to excavate and then to report
upon. So, I think you know, take it take
they should take their time and do it
methodically and sensibly.
The Tang tombs already excavated require
constant care. 97 of their delicate
murals have been removed to the Changzi
History Museum in Xi'an.
There, the startling images of the past,
preserved so long underground, can be
safeguarded for generations to come.
The murals that we have from the Tang
Imperial tombs, [music] there's really
nothing like it in scale or ambition.
But one of the reasons why people marvel
at those Tang Imperial murals is
obviously that they can
use them as a way to try and imagine
what was life like at a court. There's
so many aspects. There's the [music]
fashion. There's uh internationalism,
the cosmopolitanism, the wealth and
luxury, the pointers towards uh
architecture.
There's so many aspects of [music] life
that are brought to life by these
murals. What was it like to be a fly on
the wall at the court of the princess?
We really wouldn't have very much idea
without these amazing Tang Dynasty
Imperial murals.
It will be decades at least before the
remaining tombs of the Tang Dynasty are
opened, but the murals already revealed
have transformed how we picture Tang
China.
They have shown us what the history
books can only tell us, that this was a
cosmopolitan society connected to the
world and a military superpower
unrivaled in its age.
And though the murals may have faded and
their paints cracked, they have
preserved something more precious than
all the treasures that once filled those
silent tombs. They preserve the spark of
life.
>> [music]
[music]